I'm going to show you exactly what to
practice for the next 365 days to go
from chord beginner to chord master. You
see, if you've tried to learn chords
from one of these chord books, you've
probably failed because one, they teach
you too many chords, way more than you
actually need to know. Two, they don't
show you how these chords are actually
used in realworld songs. Three, they
don't teach you the chords in the best
order. Four, they don't tell you how to
actually make the chords sound good at
the piano. And five, worst of all, they
don't show you how to practice these
chords so that you can confidently get
them in your fingers. But if you follow
the exact path that I've designed for
you in this video, you'll go from Kevin
the Quirky Chord Kid to Ken the Cool
Chord King. Each week for the next year,
you're going to learn a new essential
chord, how to make the chord sound good,
how it's used on realworld songs, and
how to practice it. By the end of this
video, you're going to know the 52 most
important chords, how to play them in
any key, how to use them on any song,
and how to make them sound amazing on
any chord progression. If you're tired
of playing the same chords, you don't
know how to practice them, you're
overwhelmed by the amount of online
material teaching chords, you're lost
and confused about chords, or you simply
don't have that much time to practice,
this lesson is for you. In as little as
five minutes a day, you can master all
52 chords. But the most important thing
is that you stick with it. I encourage
you to come back to this video every day
because I'm going to be guiding you
through each lesson and showing you
exactly how to practice each chord. I
promise that if you stick to my plan,
you will see massive improvements in
your chord playing in the next year. So,
you ready to get started? Let's do it.
First, let's go over the overall
practice plan. The goal will be to focus
on one new chord each week and master it
at the piano. Every day of the week,
you'll practice this chord in two new
keys. And by the end of six days, you
will have practiced the chord in all 12
keys. Now, on day seven, you can take a
break or you can review the chord that
you just learned in all 12 keys. Now,
you have three options for how deeply
you want to learn your chords. Level one
is your basic understanding of the
chords. And for this level, I recommend
that you play the chords basically the
way they're written in the sheet music.
Level two understanding will be even
deeper. And so for this level of
understanding, I recommend that you
practice the chords in both hands.
Finally, level three will be your
deepest level of understanding these
chords. And so for this level, I
recommend that you practice the chords
in both hands and you play all
inversions. Now, I do want to mention
that some of these chords are already
played with both hands. And so, in this
case, you're already practicing it this
way. Also, some of the chords cannot be
easily played in inversions. So, be sure
to watch this entire lesson video
because I'm going to tell you which
exercises to play in inversions and
which ones you do not need to play in
inversions. Lastly, let's go over my
recommended practice goals. I recommend
five to 15 minutes per day of practice
to truly master these chords. How do you
know when you're ready to move on? Well,
I recommend that you set a metronome to
50 to 60 BPM. And if you can play one
chord per beat, then you're ready to
move on to the next exercise. When you
finish each lesson, I recommend that you
put a little check mark or the date in
the box below the exercise. And you will
find this in the downloadable lesson
sheet music. This is only available for
our members at Piano with Johnny, but if
you're not a member, you can, of course,
fill out a practice log using a
spreadsheet or just using a simple piece
of paper. Lastly, you can go at a faster
pace through this one-year plan. For
example, if you hit the goal tempo
early, you can move on to the next
exercise. And many of our students at
Piano with Johnny can complete a
one-year lesson plan in six months or
maybe even three months if they're
moving at a faster pace. So feel free to
go at your own pace. You can go faster
than the one-year plan. You can also go
slower and you could do this in 16
months, 18 months. So go at your own
pace. But before we dive into week
number one, if you're enjoying this
video, please hit the like button. And
if you're new to the channel, be sure to
subscribe for more videos just like
this. Welcome to week number one. And
this week you're going to learn major
chords. These are arguably the most
important chords because they are used
in tons of tunes like Can You Feel the
Love Tonight.
The way that you play a major chord is
that you start on a note like C. And you
go up four half steps. 1 2 3 4. And then
up three half steps. 1 2 3. And you have
what's called a C major. Now, to
practice this at a basic level, you
simply play the chord like this. If you
want to practice at level two, you're
going to play it in both hands like
this. And if you want to practice it at
level three, you're going to play all of
the inversions. So, we have what's
called root position. Then you put the C
on the top, first inversion. And then
you put the E on the top, second
inversion. And then you can bring it
down to your inversions. So on day
number one of week number one, you're
going to play C major and D flat major.
Day two, you're going to play D major
and E flat major. Day three, you're
going to play E major and F major. Day
four, you're going to play F sharp major
and G major. Day five, you're going to
play A flat major and A major. And day
six, you're going to play B flat major
and B major. Now, for each of these
lessons, I'm not going to play through
each day's exercises at level two or
level three because this video will turn
into hours long. But if you wanted to
practice at level two on day two, you
would play D major and you would do both
hands, all of the inversions. Do you see
it? And then you would do E flat, both
hands, all of the inversions. Okay? So,
there's a bit of putting this together
on your own. If you want to practice at
level three, you do need to figure out
the inversions for each of these chords.
But if you cannot figure out your chord
inversions, that's okay. You can learn
them in our level one foundations
learning track over at pianowithjny.com.
I'll put a link to that below. I also
want to mention that as you practice
your chords, you can practice
arpeggiating them. And here's what this
means. When I taught you these chords,
you played all the notes together. These
are called block chords. But you can
play them broken or arpeggiated. Okay?
And this can be very valuable. Let's say
you want to play your chords like this,
right? It's important to practice
arpeggiation. So, you can add to these
exercises
breaking up the chord in each inversion.
Okay? Again, this is optional if you
want that level three understanding and
you want to practice arpeggiating. And
once again, I'm not going to arpeggiate
every single chord for every single day
for this entire year because this video
will turn very long. But you should be
able to figure out how to break up the
notes of each chord. All right, welcome
to week number two. You've got one week
down, 51 to go. For week number two,
you're going to look at minor chords.
And minor chords are very sad sounding
chords. They're used on tunes like Mad
World.
So, the way to play a minor chord is
that you start on a note like C. You go
up three half steps, 1 2 3. And then you
go up four half steps, 1 2 3 4. And you
have what's called a C minor chord. Now,
for level one practice, you'll play the
chord like this. For level two, you'll
do it in both hands. And then for level
three, you'll play the inversions.
And once again, you can also arpeggiate
these chords.
And you can also bring it down.
So on day number one, you're going to
practice C minor and C sharp minor. On
day two, you're going to practice D
minor and E flat minor. On day number
three, you're going to practice E minor
and F minor. On day four, you'll
practice Fsharp minor and G minor. Day
number five, you'll practice Gsharp
minor and A minor. And day number six,
you'll practice B flat minor and B
minor. Welcome to week number three. And
in this week, you're going to learn
diminished chords. Diminished chords are
very unsettling chords.
If you watch some of the old black and
white films,
okay? And it's like a train scene. The
train's coming and you got to get the
the gal off the tracks. That is often
times a sound that you'll that you'll
hear are these
diminished chords. Okay, they're also
used on tunes like Maple Leaf Frag.
Okay, the beginning of the tune opens
with a diminished chord. Okay, so we're
going to learn these very simple
diminished triads. So, how do you play a
diminished triad? Well, you start on a
C. You go up three half steps. 1 2 3.
And then you go up three more half
steps. 1 2 3. and you have what's called
a C diminished. Okay. Now, for level one
practice, just play it in your right
hand. For level two, you can play it in
both hands. And for level three, you're
going to play inversions. So, for
inversions, you bring it up like this.
Okay? Make sense?
Very simple to play. So, how do you
practice this? Well, on day one, I
recommend that you practice C diminished
and C sharp diminished. On day two, I
recommend that you practice D diminished
and then D sharp diminished. Day three
will be E diminished and F diminished.
Day four will be Fsharp diminished and G
diminished. Day five will be uh G sharp
diminished to A diminished. And finally
day six will be B flat diminished to B
diminished. Okay? And once again, as you
practice these sets of chords each day,
you can choose your level of
understanding. So, for example, on day
three, you have E diminished and F
diminished. You could play it like that.
That's great. You could do both hands,
right? And then like that. And you can
do the inversions. This is the deep
understanding. You got to play
inversions of these chords. That's E
diminished, right? You can also break it
up.
And then you do the same thing for F.
You block it.
You with me? You can bring it down and
then you break it up.
All right, welcome to week number four.
And this week you're going to learn
augmented chords. And augmented chords
are really cool chords
that have this sound to them. Okay? Uh
they're oftentimes used in the whole
tone scale.
If you want to get a dreamy sound,
if you heard this in movies or films,
this scale comes from two augmented
chords. It's also used on lots of tunes
like you are so beautiful.
You hear that?
That is the sound of your augmented
chord. So, how do you play an augmented
chord? Well, you start on your C. You go
up four half steps. One, two, three,
four. And then you go up four more half
steps. One, two, three, four. And you
have what is called a C augmented chord.
Okay. Now, once again, you have three
levels to practice this. You can play it
one hand, you can play it two hands, or
you can play the inversions
up the piano and down the piano. And
once again, you can do them blocked, you
can do them broken.
Either one is fine. I also want to
mention fingering. When you're seeing me
play these chords, you may notice that
I'm changing my fingering. And that's
actually something that I encourage you
to do because there are various ways to
finger chords. And you want to have
versatility to be able to finger them in
multiple ways. So, for example, on this
diminish chord, you could play it like
this. You could play it like that. You
could play it like that. Okay? And so
what I want you to do as you're
practicing these is to change up your
fingering so that you have versatility.
This is very important if you want to be
a piano player is to not get locked into
fingering chords this one way. You want
to have multiple options. So on day
number one, I recommend that you
practice C augmented and D flat
augmented. On day number two, I
recommend that you practice D augmented
and E flat augmented. Day three, I
recommend that you practice E augmented
and F augmented. Day four, I recommend
that you practice Fsharp augmented and G
augmented. Day five, I recommend that
you practice A flat augmented and A
augmented. And finally, on day six, I
recommend that you practice B flat
augmented and B augmented. And once
again, you can practice this at
different levels. For example, on day
five, you have a flat augmented and a
augmented. Once again, you could do
single hands, you could do both hands,
or you could do inversions. So, you
would do a flat,
right? You could also arpeggiate it.
And then you have a same thing. You can
do it blocked like this. You seeing it?
or you can arpeggiate it. Now, before we
move on to next week, I do want to
mention that one of the best ways to
practice major and minor chords is to
practice them from within a key.
Meaning, instead of going up in these
half steps, it's really useful to take a
key like the key of C major and practice
all of the chords that come from that
key. And you'll discover that every key
has major chords, minor chords, and
diminished chords. And this can be
extremely useful because when you look
at most songs, usually they use major
and minor chords, but these chords come
from a key. And so if you want to learn
how to play major and minor chords from
within a key, I recommend that you check
out our beginner foundations learning
track at piano.com.
In this learning track, I walk you
through each key, the key of C major, F
major, G major, and I teach you all of
the major and minor chords that come
from each key. And this will equip you
to playing realworld songs with major
and minor chords. We talk about diminish
chords as well. We talk about chord
progressions. I show you how to play a
tune in that key, how to play inversions
of the chords, and then how to basically
make a lei your own. And then I show you
how to play in different styles like
jazz, blues, pop, rock, uh, Latin. So
much fun. And we really go deep on each
key so that you truly understand these
chords. So I'll put a link to that
below. All right, welcome to week number
five. And this week you're going to
learn about sus 2 chords. And sus two
chords are really cool sounding chords.
They have this sound to them and they're
used on lots of tunes. For example, on
the tune Faithfully by Journey, it has
this little riff.
Okay? And basically what they're doing
is they're playing a C major chord to a
C sus 2. So it has an amazing sound. So
how do you play these chords? Well, you
start on C, you go up two steps, and
then you go up one, two, three, four,
five steps up to your G. And this is
called a C sus 2. Okay. Now, you can
play it with your right hand, you can
play it with both hands, and you can do
your inversions. Inversions get a little
tricky because you get these really
spread out notes like this. Okay? So,
you got lots of options here. Once
again, you can arpeggiate
the notes as well. It gets a little
tricky. You got to kind of think ahead,
but
they're a lot of fun to play. Now, on
day one, you're going to practice C sus
2 and D flat sus 2. Okay. Day two,
you're going to practice D sus 2 and E
flat sus 2. Day three, you'll practice E
sus 2 and F sus 2. Day four, you'll
practice F sharp sus 2 and G sus 2. Day
five, you'll practice a flat sus 2 and A
sus 2. And finally, on day six, you'll
practice B flat sus 2 and B sus 2. All
right, welcome to week number six. And
this week, you're going to learn all
about sus 4 chords. and sus four chords
are very cool chords if you're playing a
chord progression in C
and you go to that five chord G.
It's a really cool way of playing your G
chord
to kind of make it sound unresolved and
it's used on lots of tunes. For example,
the tune Crazy Little Thing Called Love
by Queen opens with the sus four chords.
You hear that?
Those are sus chords. So, how do you
play a sus chord? Well, you start on C.
You go up 1 2 3 4 five half steps. And
then you go up one, two half steps, and
you have what's called a C sus4. Once
again, you can play it with your right
hand, both hands. You can also
arpeggiate it up the piano like this.
Okay, lots of great options here. Now,
on day one, I recommend that you
practice C sus4 and D flat sus4. Day
two, I recommend that you practice D sus
4 and E flat sus 4. Day three will be E
sus 4 and F sus 4. Day four will be F
sharp sus 4 and G sus 4. Next day will
be a flat sus 4 and a sus4. And finally,
day six will be B flat sus 4 and B sus4.
All right, welcome to week number seven.
This week, you're going to learn about
major 6 chords. And major 6 chords are
really cool chords that allow you to
color a C major
like this. And if you ever wanted to
play a run on C,
you can add an A to this chord to turn
it into a C6 chord. It has a very happy,
colorful sound, and it's used on lots of
tunes. For example, the tune The Way You
Look Tonight.
Okay, that first chord
is a six chord. It's a C6 chord. So, has
a very beautiful sound. So, how do you
play a major 6 chord? Well, you start on
the E. You're going to play a C major
triad that you already learned, except
you're going to add the A, which is a
whole step above that top note. This is
a C6 chord. Okay? Now, you can practice
it in one hand, you can do two hands, or
you can do inversions. Okay? And for
this one, you're going to have four ways
to play it. You're going to have 1 2 3
and four. Okay? So you have slightly
more inversions here when you're
practicing it. Now on day one, you're
going to practice C6 and D flat 6. Day
two will be D6 and E flat 6. Uh day
three will be E6 and F6.
Day four will be Fsharp 6 and G6. Day
five will be A flat 6 and A6. And day
six will be B flat 6 and B6. Welcome to
week number eight. And this week you're
going to learn about minor 6 chords. And
minor 6 chords are beautiful chords that
you can use to color an ordinary minor
chord like this and make it sound like
this.
Okay? Is a beautiful sounding chord.
It's used in lots of styles. And one
tune that uses this chord out the gates
is Summertime.
Super beautiful. So, how do you play a
minor 6 chord? Well, you're going to
play a C minor except you're going to
add the six, the A to this chord. And
it's very simple. You just add the note
a whole step above the top note of your
minor chord. Okay? Once again, you can
do single hands, you can do both hands,
and you can do inversions.
Okay, the ver inversions get a little
tricky because you have more inversions
than you did on your minor chord. All
right, so for day one, you're going to
practice C minor 6 and D flat minor 6.
Get a little little interesting here.
Then on day two, you're going to have D
minor 6 and E flat minor 6. Day three,
you'll have E minor 6 and F minor 6. Day
four, you'll have F sharp minor 6 and G
minor 6. Day five, you'll have a flat
minor 6 and A minor 6. And finally, on
day six, you'll have B flat minor 6 and
B minor 6. Welcome to week number nine,
where you're going to learn all about
major 7 chords. And major 7 chords are
beautiful chords where you can take a
simple chord like C major and you could
play it like this.
Okay. It's a beautiful way to color your
chord and it's used on lots of tunes.
For example, the Norah Jones tune, Don't
Know Why,
starts on a B flat major 7 chord. So,
has a very beautiful sound. So, how do
you play a major 7th chord? Well, you
start on the C. You play a C major
chord, except you're going to add a note
on top of that, the B. Okay? And the
easiest way to think of this is that
that top note is just a half step below
the root. In this case, the root is C.
So, you add the B to it and you have
what's called a C major 7 chord. Okay?
Now, you could do level one, you could
do level two, or you can do level three
with these inversions. Look at all at
all these beautiful inversions. Okay.
So, you have some options. Once again,
you can arpeggiate it.
You don't have to do this. It really
depends on how deeply you want to go.
So, for day number one, I recommend that
you practice C major 7 and D flat major
7. Day two will be D major 7 and E flat
major 7. Day three will be E major 7 and
F major 7. Day four will be G flat major
7 and G major 7. Day five will be A flat
major 7 and A major 7. And finally on
day six will be B flat major 7 and B
major 7. Welcome to week number 10. And
this week you're going to learn minor
7th chords. And minor 7th chords are a
really beautiful way of coloring a minor
chord. You can take an ordinary minor
chord like this and make it sound like
this.
Okay. It's used on lots of tunes. For
example, the Carol King tune, I feel the
earth.
Okay. The very first chord in the tune
is a minor 7th chord. So, how do you
play a minor 7 chord? Well, you start on
C. You play a C minor triad, which you
already learned, and then you're gonna
add the seventh to this. The seventh is
a whole step down from the root. So you
take the C, you go down a whole step to
B flat, and you have what's called a
minor 7 chord. Okay? So here's level
one, here's level two, and level three
is your inversions. You see them? Once
again, you can practice these on your
own. You can break it up.
I'm not going to do every single one,
but I'm showing you some ideas for how
deep you can go. Okay, so day one,
you're going to do C minor 7 and D flat
minor 7. Day two will be D minor 7 and E
flat minor 7. Day three will be E minor
7 and F minor 7. Day four will be F
sharp minor 7 and G minor 7. Day five
will be a flat minor 7 and a minor 7.
And finally on day six, you'll have B
flat minor 7 and B minor 7. All right,
welcome to week 11. This week you're
going to learn dominant seventh chords.
Arguably the most important seventh
chord if you want to play jazz, blues,
and other styles. It is used a lot in
the blues. So, if I start playing the
blues,
guess what? I'm playing a dominant
seventh chord. It's also used on classic
tunes like Atlas.
Okay, that first chord is a dominant
seven chord. So, how do you play a
dominant seven chord? Well, we're gonna
start on C. We're gonna play a C major
triad. And then we're gonna add the note
a whole step below the root. So that's
going to be a B flat. Okay. So this is a
C dominant 7th chord. It's also called
simply a C7. So if you see a C7 or a C
dominant 7, it means the same thing.
Okay? C dominant 7. So you can do level
one, level two or level three are your
inversions. All right. Now on day one, I
recommend that you practice C7 and D
flat 7. Day two will be D7 and E flat 7.
Day three will be E7 and F7.
Day four will be G flat 7 and G7. Day
five will be A flat 7 and A7. And day
six will be B flat 7 and B7. All right,
welcome to week number 12. And this week
you're going to learn about diminished
seventh chords. And you actually already
learned about diminished chords, but
diminished seventh chords have an even
cooler sound. These chords are very hip.
They're used in lots of tunes like White
Christmas.
You hear that chord? I'ming. That's a
diminished chord. Okay. It's also used
on kind of oldtime jazz tunes.
That second chord,
that's a diminished seventh chord. Okay.
So, how do you play a diminished seventh
chord? Well, we play a diminished chord,
which you learned earlier, except we're
going to add one more minor third
interval on the top. So, from this F
sharp, we go 1 2 3 to the A, and you
have what's called a diminished seventh
chord. Now, you might be wondering,
Johnny, why is this a seventh chord?
Because this A is six notes above the
root. Well, technically it is a double
flat 7th. It's as if you took this B and
made a a double flat. Okay? But the way
I think about it is a simple diminished
triad and we add the sixth interval from
the root. Okay? So, we have level one,
we have level two, and we have level
three with our inversions. So for
practice, day one will be C diminished
7, C sharp diminished 7. Okay. Day two
will be D diminished 7, E flat
diminished 7. Day three will be E
diminished and F diminished 7. Day four
will be F sharp diminished 7 and G
diminish 7. Day five will be G sharp
diminished 7 and A diminished 7. And
finally day six will be B flat
diminished 7 and B diminished 7. Welcome
to week number 13 where you're going to
learn about half diminished seventh
chords. And these chords are very
beautiful dark sounding chords. For
example, if you had a minor tune in C,
it's very common to go to this chord on
a two chord like a D.
For example, on the tune beautiful love,
that first chord is a half diminished
chord. Okay. So, how do you play a half
diminished chord? Well, you play a
diminished chord. You already learned
this, except instead of playing the A,
which comes from the C diminished 7th,
we actually raise that top note a half
step. So, this is what's called a C half
diminished 7. It's also called a C minor
7 with a flat five. Okay? So, you have
two ways of describing this chord.
Usually in classical music they call it
a C half diminish 7 and in jazz we call
it a C minor 7 flat 5. But is a very
important chord to learn. You can do
level one, you can do level two and
level three are your inversions. Okay.
Lots of options here. Okay. Now in terms
of practicing it, day one I recommend
that you play C half diminish 7,
C sharp half diminish 7 or D flat. Okay.
Day two will be D half diminished seven
and E flat half diminished seven. Day
three will be E half diminish 7 and F
half diminish 7. Day four will be F
sharp half diminish 7 and G half
diminish 7. Day five will be G uh sharp
half diminish 7 and A half diminish 7.
And finally on day six, it will be B
flat half diminished 7 and B half
diminished seven. All right, welcome to
week 14. And this week you're going to
learn the minor major 7 chord. And you
might be thinking, Johnny, minor major,
what are you talking about? I know minor
and I know major, but that's not this
chord. The minor major seventh chord is
a really cool seventh chord. also known
as the spy chord because it has this
sound.
It has a very mysterious sound to it and
it's also used in lots of tunes like my
funny Valentine.
That second chord, My Funny Valentine,
that is your minor major 7 chord. Okay.
So, how do you play this chord? Well, we
play a C minor in our right hand, except
we're going to add the major 7 to this
chord. So, we're actually going to add
the B natural to this chord. Okay? It's
a less common chord. You're not going to
see this one as much, but it is
prevalent enough that it is worth
learning. Okay? So, it's a minor triad
with a major 7th. That's why we call it
a minor major 7 chord. Okay? So you have
level one, you've got level two, and of
course you can do the inversions. The
inversions will sound a little weird,
but you can practice it this way. Okay.
For day one, you're going to practice C
minor major 7 and C sharp minor major 7.
Okay. Day two will be D minor major 7
and E flat minor major 7. Day three will
be E minor major 7 and F minor major 7.
Day four will be Fsharp minor major 7
and G minor major 7. Day five will be G
sharp minor major 7 and A minor major 7.
And day six will be B flat minor major 7
and B minor major 7. Now, if you want to
go deeper on your seventh chords, major
7, dominant 7, minor 7, and you really
want to understand them in more detail,
I recommend that you check out our level
four foundations learning track. In this
learning track, we go deep on each one
of these chords. So, you're going to do
a study on major 7, dominant 7, minor
7th chords. But you're not just going to
learn the chords, you're going to learn
essential exercises. I'm going to walk
you through each exercise. We're going
to practice it from a variety of angles
and contexts so that you really
understand it deeply. We're going to
work through chord progressions that use
these chords. We're going to work
through how to play inversions. And then
you're going to learn how to play these
chords on lead sheets. These are tunes
that you're going to see in a jazz book
or in a fake book so you really
understand this at a deep level. And
once again, we go through every single
chord, diminish and half diminished
seventh chords. And then this is our
application course playing lead sheets
with these chords. And by the way, in
this lead sheet course, we go through
the top eight chord progressions that
you will find across almost all tunes.
So this will prepare you for the real
world. I'll put a link to this learning
track below. All right, welcome to week
number 15. And this week you're going to
learn major nine chords. These are
beautiful chords that can be used to
color ordinary major chords. For
example, let's say you have a C major.
You want to really color it. You could
play it like this.
Isn't that absolutely gorgeous? And this
chord is used on lots of tunes like Girl
from Meima.
That first chord is an F major 9 chord.
So, they're absolutely beautiful. So,
how do you play a major 9 chord? Well,
basically you're going to start on the C
and you're going to play a C major 7
like you learned earlier, except we're
going to add one more note to this
chord, the D. Okay? And this is the
ninth of the chord. And you might be
wondering, Johnny, I don't understand.
Why are we adding this note? Well, if
you recall earlier when you learned
major chords like C major, we skip a
note from the C major scale. We skip the
D and play the E, and then we skip the F
and play the G. And this forms a major
chord. It's called tertian harmony or
tertiary harmony. It's how we build
chords. They're built in in third
intervals, right? 1 2 3 1 2 3. Well, if
you continue this and you play another
third, you end up with a major 7 chord.
But if you do it one more time and skip
this C and play the D, you end up with a
major 9 chord. And that's because this
is a ninth interval. Okay? Okay. So, we
call this a C major 9 chord. Okay. And
one more thing I want to say about ninth
chords is when you play something like a
C major 9, it includes all of those
notes where you're building up to the
ninth. So, if you say C major 9, it
usually includes a C, E, G, and a B and
the D. Now, you can omit, you can remove
notes. That's not uncommon. But
generally if you play a ninth chord it
implies the presence of these lower
notes. Okay. So that is a C major 9
chord. You could play it like this,
right? You could play it like that with
just the single note in the right hand.
You can also play it like this. Okay. So
this is where you can start to do lots
of different fingering options. And I
encourage you to try some different
ones. The one that I recommend is this.
You're going to put the C on the bottom
and you're going to put the chord there.
But once again, you could play it like
this. You could play it like this. And
you could play it like that. Okay. Now,
with this chord, you're already playing
it with two hands. You kind of need two
hands to play it anyway. But you could
play inversions. You could take the top
part of the chord and play it like this
and then like this and then like this.
Okay? So, if you want to practice at a
deeper level, you keep that C on the
bottom and you play all of your
inversions on the top. All right? So,
how do you practice this? Day number
one, you're going to do C major 9 and D
flat major 9. You see it? Day two will
be D major 9 and E flat major 9. Day
three will be E major 9 and F major 9.
Day four will be G flat major 9 and G
major 9. Day five will be A flat major 9
and A major 9. And finally on day six
will be B flat major 9 and B major 9.
Okay. Now I want to show you a a quick
little trick to remembering this chord.
You may have already noticed this, but
on my C major 9, if you just play the
top half of the chord, you might
recognize this. This is an E minor 7.
Okay? And so this can be a really easy
way to remembering your major 9 chord if
you think I'm going to play a minor 7th
chord starting on the third of the
chord. So, for example, if I wanted to
figure out F major 9, I can start on the
third of the chord and play an A minor
7. Just a little trick there that can
help you out. All right, welcome to week
number 16. And this week, you're going
to learn about dominant nine chords. And
dominant nine chords are very hip
chords. It's a really cool way to color
your blues chords. So, if you're playing
a blues,
okay, you can use ninth chords.
And they're also used on pop tunes. For
example, the Michael Bubé tune,
Everything.
This chord here is a dominant nine
chord. It has an amazing sound to it.
So, how do you play a dominant nine
chord? Well, you're going to play a C
dominant seventh chord. I taught you
this earlier, except you're going to add
a D to it. And remember, the D is a
ninth interval above the C. It comes
from the C major scale. You could also
think of it as the second note or the
two of the major scale. So once again,
C7, you're going to add the nine uh
there. Okay. Now, in terms of the
fingering, you've got lots of options.
You could do that, you could do that,
you could do that. For this lesson, I
recommend that you play it like this.
Left hand here. And once again, you can
do inversions if you want to understand
it at a deeper level. Okay. So day one I
recommend that you play C9 and D flat 9.
Day two will be D9 and E flat 9. Day
three will be E9 and F9. Day four will
be G flat 9 and G9. Day five will be A
flat 9 and A9. And day six will be B
flat 9 and B9. All right, welcome to
week 17. And this week you're going to
learn all about minor 9th chords. And
minor 9 chords are beautiful chords that
you can use to color an ordinary minor
chord like a C minor. And you can make
it sound like this.
Okay. It's used in lots of tunes. One
tune that comes to mind is Billy Jean by
Michael Jackson.
Okay. If you listen to the band, that
first chord is a minor 9 chord. Okay.
It's very beautiful, very hip. So, how
do you play a minor 9? Well, we're going
to start on C. We're going to play a C
minor 7 that you learned earlier, except
we're going to add the ninth. Once
again, is the D. Okay? It's the same
note that you've been learning. This is
a minor 9 chord. It includes the 1 3 5 7
and nine. Okay? Once again, you can use
different fingering options. I recommend
this one. And you can play inversions
with the root
in the left hand. Okay? So for day one C
minor 9 and C sharp minor 9. Day two is
D minor 9 and E flat minor 9. Day three
is E minor 9 and F minor 9. Day four is
Fsharp minor 9 and G minor 9. Day five
is G sharp minor 9 and A minor 9. And
day six is B flat minor 9 and B minor 9.
All right. Welcome to week number 18
where you're going to learn about minor
11 chords. And minor 11 chords once
again are a beautiful way of coloring
minor chords like C minor. You can turn
it from this into
this. Okay.
Beautiful way of playing a minor chord.
And you can do this on lots of tunes.
For example, the tune Hark the Herald
Angels Sing
on that second chord.
This is called a D minor 11. So, it's a
very useful chord. So, how do you play
this chord? Well, basically, you're
going to play a C minor 9, which I
taught you earlier, except we're going
to add the 11th to this chord, which is
the F. And once again, we are simply
stacking thirds from uh, in this case,
the major scale. 1 3 5 7 9 11. Of
course, the third is flat and the
seventh is flat, but the 11 comes from
the major scale. You could also think of
it as the four. 1 2 3 4. Okay. So, this
is a C minor 11. It includes the 1 3 5 7
and the nine. Okay. In terms of how to
play it, you could play it like this. In
the sheet music, we have it notated like
this. Okay. And once again, you could
play some in different inversions. It
gets a little tricky, right? because
usually pianists won't do like this.
They try to cluster the notes together.
So, I do not recommend that you play
inversions of these chords. Uh, unless
you really want to. You could try to get
the 11 in like this and do some
clusters. See what I'm doing? But that
gets a little overkill to try to get all
these notes in the chord. So, I
recommend that you just play it like
this. Okay. So, on day number one,
you're going to play C minor 11 and C
sharp minor 11. Day two will be D minor
11 and E flat minor 11. Day three will
be E minor 11 and F minor 11. Day four
will be F# minor 11 and G minor 11. Uh
day five will be G sharp minor 11 and A
minor 11. And then finally on day six
we'll have B flat minor 11 and B minor
11. All right, welcome to week 19. This
week you're going to learn about major
13 chords. And major 13 chords are a
beautiful way of playing major chords.
So instead of playing C major like this,
you could play it like this.
Right? Very beautiful, very colorful.
And there's lots of tunes that you could
do this on. For example, you could do
this on the tune that's all
that first chord. D.
This is a major 13 chord. Very colorful
chord. So, how do you play a major 13
chord? Well, you're going to play your
major 7th chord that I taught you
earlier. You're going to add the ninth
to this chord, and you're going to add
the 13th to this chord. This is actually
a 13th interval above the root. Um, and
we're skipping the 11th because it
doesn't sound good in the chord. One way
I like to think of the 13th is the six.
Okay? But this is indeed a C major 13
chord. It includes the 1 3 5 7 9 and the
13. Okay. So, how do you practice this?
Well, on day one, I recommend that you
do C major 13 and D flat major 13. Okay.
Day two will be D major 13 and E flat
major 13. Uh, day three will be E major
13 and F major 13.
Day four will be G flat major 13 and G
major 13.
Day five will be A flat major 13 and A
major 13. And day six will be B flat
major 13 and B major 13. Okay. Now you
can try playing inversions on these. For
example, on the C, right? If you want to
grab as many of these notes as you can,
it gets tricky because right, you have
all of these notes and so it can be
really tricky to grab all of these
inversions. If you want to try it, they
turn into pretty big clusters
like this. So, I don't necessarily
recommend that you practice it because
again, it's a lot of notes. I think it's
more important to understand the basic
notes so that when you see the chord,
you know which notes you can add to your
playing. All right, welcome to week 20
where you're going to learn about minor
13 chords. Minor 13 chords are a very
hip way of coloring ordinary minor
chords like this to make it sound like
this.
Okay, it's used in a lot of funk music
and it just has this very bluesy uh cool
sound to it. So, how do you play a minor
13 chord? Well, you're going to play
that C minor 7. You're going to put the
nine in and you're going to add the 13,
the A, which I just taught you. Okay,
once again, you're already playing it
with two hands. You can try to grab
different inversions of these chords,
but it does become a lot, right, to try
to get all the notes in. So, I just
recommend that you play it like this.
And in terms of practicing it, I
recommend that you go uh C minor 13 to D
flat minor 13. That's day one. Day two
is D minor 13 to E flat minor 13. Day
three is E minor 13 to F minor 13. Day
four is F sharp minor 13 to G minor 13.
Day five is A flat minor 13 to A
minor 13. And day six is going to be B
flat minor 13 to B
minor 13. All right, welcome to week
number 21. And this week you're going to
learn dominant 13 chords. And dominant
13 chords are very hip ways of playing a
dominant seventh chord. So for example,
instead of playing a C7 like this, I
could play it like this.
Okay? It's a much more colorful way of
playing a seventh chord. It's used a lot
in the blues. So how do you play a
dominant 13 chord? Well, you're going to
play a C7 that I already taught you.
You're going to put the nine in there,
and you're going to put the 13 in there.
Okay? So this should look pretty
familiar to you. And that is a D13
chord. It's a dominant 13 chord. Okay.
In terms of practicing it, day one will
be C13,
D flat 13. Day two will be D13 and E
flat 13.
Day three will be E13 and F13.
Day four will be Fsharp 13 and G13.
Day five will be A flat 13 and A13.
And day six will be B flat 13 and B13.
All right, welcome to week number 22.
This week you're going to learn about 69
chords. And 6ix9ine chords are a
beautiful way of coloring major chords.
And you can take a C major like this and
make it sound like this.
Okay, it's a very happy sound. It's used
on lots of tunes. For example, Silent
Night.
That first chord is a C69 chord. Very
beautiful way of playing major chords.
So, how do you play this chord? Well,
it's very simple. You're going to play a
C major in the left hand. You're going
to add a six to it, the A, and then
you're going to put a ninth on the top,
the D. Okay? And this makes it a C69
chord. Okay? Really beautiful. Um, now
in terms of practicing this, you're
going to have it in both hands. You
could put the top of the chord here and
you could practice inversions of this.
This actually would work with
inversions. Usually for inversions, I
remove the root from the chord. So you
could practice it like this if you want
to get comfortable and confident with
this chord. Okay. So terms of practicing
it, day one, I recommend C69 like this
and D flat 69 like this. Day two will be
D69
and E flat 69.
Day three will be E69 and F69.
Day four will be F sharp 6-9 and G69.
Day five will be a flat 6-9 and A69.
B flat 69. This is day six and B 69. All
right. Welcome to week number 23. And
this week you're going to learn about
minor 69 chords. Once again, these are
beautiful chords and a way to color
ordinary minor chords. For example, you
could take a C minor like this and you
could play it like this.
Really beautiful. It's used on lots of
tunes. For example, Lullabi of Birdland.
That first chord is a minor 69 chord.
Okay. So, how do you play this chord?
Well, it's a minor 6 chord. So, you have
a C minor with a six and you put the
nine on the top. Okay. Very important
chord. Once again, you could put those
top notes in your right hand. And you
could play it like this if you want to
practice some inversions of this chord.
It does get a little bit tricky, but if
you again, if you want to master this,
you can play it at this level. Okay. So,
how do you practice this? Well, day one
that'll be C minor 69 and D flat minor
69. Okay. Day two will be D minor 69 and
E flat minor 69.
Day three will be E minor 69
and F minor 69.
Day four will be F# minor 69 and G minor
69.
Day five will be a flat minor 69 and a
minor 69. and day six will be B flat
minor 69 and B minor 69. Now, one thing
that I want to mention when you're
playing the 9th, the 11th, and the 13th
of chord, these are called chord
extensions. And they're basically notes
that you can add to the chord to make
them sound more beautiful and
interesting. And if you want to go
deeper on these chords, you really want
to understand them and get them in your
playing, I recommend that you check out
our level five foundations learning
track. In this learning track, we go
into a lot of detail on these chords
right down here in our extensions and
alterations learning track. And the
course that I recommend is our piano
chord extensions course. In this course,
we go through exercises to master your
chord extensions. And then if you go
back, you're going to learn how to apply
your chord extensions to lead sheets
with our application course. Really
important if you want to go deep on
this. So, I'll put a link to that
learning track below. All right, welcome
to week number 24. And this week you're
going to start learning about altered
dominant chords. And altered dominant
chords are basically when you're playing
a chord like G7 and you want to make it
sound extra cool
like that. You're going to add these
altered notes or alterations to the
chord. Okay? So this week you're going
to learn your first alteration which is
called the flat nine. And these notes
are typically added whenever you're on a
five chord. So if I'm in the key of C
and I go to a G chord, right? and I want
to color it,
right? These are ways to color this
chord. Likewise, if I'm in the key of C
and I go to a six chord, like an A7, and
I want to color this chord, right? You
can add these alter notes to basically
any dominant chord. So, how do you play
a dominant flat N chord? Well, you play
a C7 that I taught you earlier. You take
the D, you flat it. That is the flat N.
Okay? It's that simple. Okay? Now, you
can play the top four notes with your
right hand. And now you can practice
your inversions if you would like. Well,
once again, that is up to you how deep
you want to go. Okay. So, day one will
be C7 flat 9 and D flat 7 flat 9. Day
two will be D7 flat 9 and E7 flat 9. Day
three will be E7 flat 9 and F7 flat 9.
Day four will be F# 7 flat 9 and G7 flat
9.
Day five will be a flat 7 flat 9 and a7
flat 9. And finally, day six will be B
flat 7 flat 9 and B7 flat 9. All right,
welcome to week number 25. And this week
you're going to learn about dominant
sharp 9 chords. And these are really
cool chords. Once again, if you want to
color a dominant chord like a G7, you
could play it like this. This is the
sound of the dominant sharp nine. Very
crunchy, very cool. And you can resolve
to a C. You can play on multiple chords
as well. You could go
like that. Okay. Super crunchy. So, the
way that you play a dominant sharp nine
is you play a dominant seventh chord
that you already learned and then we're
going to add the D sharp, which is the
sharp nine. Okay? And the easy way to
figure this out is you just think of the
root note and you go up one, two, three
half steps. Okay? So that is a C7 sharp
9. Now in terms of playing this in both
hands, you could play it like this and
then you could practice your various
inversions, but usually we don't play
chords like this. So I do not recommend
that you play the inversions of this
chord. Once again, we're just
understanding the basic chord here. So
on day one, you're going to play C7
sharp 9 and D flat 7 sharp 9. Day two
will be D7 sharp nine and E flat 7 sharp
nine. Day three will be E7 sharp nine
and F7 sharp nine. Day four will be
Fsharp 7 sharp 9 and G7 sharp 9. Day
five will be a flat 7 sharp 9 and A7
sharp 9. And finally on day six we'll
have B flat 7 sharp 9 and B7 sharp 9.
All right, welcome to week number 26.
This week you're going to learn about
dominant sharp 11 chords. These are
beautiful chords once again that you
could use to color a dominant chord.
Instead of playing a G7 like this, you
could play it like this.
Right? This is a really interesting note
that's oftenimes added to dominant
chords. It's especially used on the two
chord. Like if I'm in the key of C and I
go to a D7 chord, you'll hear it. And
there's a really beautiful jazz tune
called Desphonado. It goes like this.
You hear the two chord, the G. That is
the sound of the dominant sharp 11
chord. So for a dominant sharp 11 chord,
what you're going to do is you're going
to play a dominant seventh chord in your
left hand, and you're going to add the
sharp 11, which is the Fsharp in the
right hand. Uh you can think of it as an
11th. Remember that F, but it's sharp.
Okay? Some people will call this a flat
five because it's the G flat, but I like
to call it the sharp 11 because
technically it is a note being usually
added to the chord. And we tend to think
of these as um modifications of our
chord extension. So C7 sharp 11. So how
do you practice this? Well, day one C7
sharp 11 and D flat 7 sharp 11. Okay.
Day two will be D7 sharp 11 and E flat 7
sharp 11. Uh day three will be E7 with a
sharp 11 and the F 7 sharp 11. Day four
will be Fsharp 7 with a sharp 11 and the
G7 with a sharp 11. Then we'll have a
flat 7 sharp 11 and a seven sharp 11.
That's day five. And day six is your B
flat 7 sharp 11 and your B7 sharp 11.
All right, week number 27, you're gonna
practice dominant flat 13 chords. And
just like our other chords, when you're
on a five chord, like a G7, you can
color it with a really cool note
like that. Really hip.
Okay, that is the sound of your dominant
flat 13 chord. So, how do you play this
chord? Well, if you play a C7, you're
going to add the A flat, which we call
the flat 13. Remember the 13 is the A.
You make that flat. Okay? Very uh cool,
very hip sounding chord. Usually with
this chord, pianists will omit the
fifth. They usually will not play this.
And if you play it like this, then you
can get some of these inversions down
here. You see this? So, you could play
it like this.
Okay? But again, that's if you are
omitting the fifth. Okay. So, how do you
practice this? Day one, this is going to
be a C7 flat 13 and a D flat 7 flat 13.
Okay. Day two will be a D7 flat 13 and
an E flat 7 flat 13. Day three will be
an E7 flat 13 and an F7 flat 13. Day
four will be an F sharp 7 flat 13 and a
G7 flat 13. Day five will be an A flat 7
flat 13 and an A7 flat 13. And finally,
day six will be a B flat 7 flat 13 and a
B7 flat 13. All right, welcome to week
28. And this week you're going to start
combining your chord alterations. And
this is where it starts to really sound
good. If I'm on a five chord, I'm going
to a C chord and I want to use more than
one chord alteration. Maybe I want this
sound.
Okay, this is the sound of multiple
chord alterations. Jazz musicians use
these all the time, and it's really
important to learn the most common uh
combinations of these chord alterations.
So, for this uh lesson here, you're
going to learn the flat 13 sharp 9
combination, which has this sound.
Okay. It's really beautiful. That's the
sound.
So, what is a dominant flat 13 sharp
nine? Well, you take your dominant
chord, you add your flat 13, and you add
your sharp nine to it. You've already
learned these, and now you're just
mixing them together. It sounds super
cool. Once again, in practice, jazz
musicians will omit the fifth to get
kind of this sound. And you could
practice inversions. You could play it
like this and then you could bring it
up. Again, most musicians won't use this
particular inversion. They will use this
one. Okay, these are called A and B
voicings. But I think it's more
important to get your bass chord like
this so you know the notes. Okay, so how
do you practice this? Day one is your C
and your D flat. Okay. Day two is your D
and your E flat.
Day three is your E and your F. And by
the way, these are big chords. F7 flat
through 13 D sharp nine. Okay. Then on
uh day four, it is Fsharp
and G.
And then day five is A flat and A. And
day six is B flat and B. All right,
welcome to week number 29. And this week
you're going to learn another very cool
uh ultrainant chord called a dominant
sharp 11 flat 9. And this is a once
again a very hip way of playing a
dominant chord. If I'm going G7 to C, I
could play it like this.
Okay, it's a very hip sound
and it just it's beautiful. It's a great
way to color your chords. So that's the
sound. So how do you play this chord?
Well, it's a C7. We're going to add the
sharp 11 F sharp and the flat N
that D flat. Okay. And by the way, an
easy way to remember this, it's like a G
flat chord over a C chord, right? G flat
major over C. Okay. It has a very hip
sound to it. All right. In terms of
playing this in inversions, I do not
recommend that you do this because there
are a lot of notes here. I think they're
adequately covered in both hands. Okay.
So, these are the notes in terms of
practicing it. Day one will be C7 and D
flat 7. Day two will be D7 and E flat 7.
Day three will be E7 and F7.
Day four will be F sharp 7 and G7.
Day five will be A flat 7 and A7. And
day six will be B flat 7 and B7. And I
want to remind you, I'm not saying all
the chord alterations, but this is a B7
sharp 11 flat 9. Okay? It's again, very
hip way of playing these dominant
chords. All right, here we are in week
number 30. And this week, you're going
to learn your last alter dominant chord.
This is one of my all-time favorite
combinations called the dominant 13 flat
9. It has a beautiful sound. Give it a
listen.
Okay. I love this sound. and it's used a
lot in intros of tunes and it's it's
that sound really really beautiful and
especially works well on ballads. So
what is a dominant 13 flat 9? Well,
basically I'm going to take my C7 chord
that I taught you earlier and I'm going
to put a 13 on it. That's the A that I
taught you, but I'm going to mix that
with a flat 9, the D flat. And you can
think of this like an A major triad over
a C. It has a very beautiful sound to
it. Okay. Um, once again, you could try
pract practicing this in some different
inversions, but it does become a lot
with all the notes. You could sort of
think of it like an A7,
but again, I recommend that you just
learn the basic notes like this and
practice it in all of your keys. Okay?
So, day one, you're going to do C1 13
flat 9 and the D uh flat 13 flat 9.
Okay? Day two will be D13 flat 9 and E
flat 13 flat 9. Day three will be E 13
flat 9 and F 13 flat 9. I know it sounds
kind of weird, but these are the chords.
Uh day four will be F# 13 flat 9 and G
13 flat 9. Day five will be a flat 13
flat 9 and A13 flat 9. And day six will
be B flat 13 flat 9 and B 13 flat 9. All
right, welcome to week 31. And this is
an exciting week because basically what
we're going to do from here forward is
we're going to cover voicings. And
voicings are basically how you play the
chords that you already learned in an
interesting way. And if you recall
earlier when you learned certain chords,
we're stacking lots of notes. It doesn't
sound very interesting. However, when
you put the notes together in a certain
way like this,
these are called voicings, and it's
basically the way that the notes get
arranged. So, this week, we're going to
start with our first rootless voicing. A
rootless voicing is a chord without a
root. And it is a common way of playing
chords
in the right hand. In this case, I'm
playing a root in my left hand, but my
right hand chord does not have a root.
Okay? So, we're going to go a little bit
faster because you already know these
chords. I'm just going to show you a
cool way of playing them. Okay, first
chord here. This is our major 9 chord.
Recall earlier you learned the C major
9. Well, in jazz, a very cool way to
play this chord is to put the seventh on
the bottom, the ninth, the third, and
the fifth. There's no root. There's no C
in it. Okay? And this is called a B
voicing because it has the seventh on
the bottom. Okay? Okay. So, you're just
going to practice your major 9 rootless
voicing chords. This is really useful
for accompaniment if you're accompanying
a singer or an an instrumentalist. So,
day one, we're going to play C major 9
and D flat major 9. Day two is D major 9
and E flat major 9. Day three is E major
9 and F major 9.
Day four is G flat major 9 and G major
9. Day five is a flat major 9 and a
major 9. And finally, day six is B flat
major 9 and B major 9. Okay. Now, with
these you can play inversions. I can go
from here and play it like this. That's
beautiful. Okay. But in jazz, there are
two voicings that are they tend we tend
to use for rootless voicings. We tend to
use what's called that B voicing with
the seventh on the bottom and the A
voicing with the third on the bottom.
So, if you're going to practice
inversions, I recommend your A voicing
and your B voicing. Your A voicing and
your B voicing. A B. All right. Welcome
to week number 32. This week, you're
going to learn your rootless minor 9
chords. And just like before, uh you
already know this chord. It's a minor 9
except we're going to play it like that.
Way cooler, way hipper to play your
chords, your minor 9 chords like this.
So, how do you play this chord? You take
your C minor 9 and you put the seventh
on the bottom and you voice it like
this. 7 9 3 and five. Okay, very
beautiful chord. Okay. And this is
called a B voicing because it has the
seventh on the bottom. Okay. And once
again, you could put the third on the
bottom and practice your AO voicing and
your B voicing if you want to do
inversions of these chords. Okay. So,
how do you practice these chords? Well,
day number one is going to be C minor 9
and C sharp minor 9. Day two will be D
minor 9, E flat minor 9. Day three will
be E minor 9 and F minor 9.
Day four will be F# minor 9 and G minor
9. Day five will be G sharp minor 9 and
A minor 9. And finally on day six we'll
have B flat minor 9 and B minor 9. All
right, welcome to week number 33. And
this week we're going to talk about
rootless major 69 chords. Once again, uh
these are chords that you know and it's
just a beautiful way of playing it using
rootless voicings. Here's the sound of
major 69 chords,
right? You hear that?
It's a beautiful way to color your major
chords. So, you already know this chord.
Remember a C major 69 is this. And we're
going to talk about voicings. How do you
voice the chord as a rootless voicing?
Well, you're going to put the six on the
bottom, the nine, the three, and the
five. This is called a B voicing because
it has the sixth on the bottom.
Likewise, you could put the A voicing
with the third on the bottom. Okay. C69.
Very common chord. How do you practice
this? Uh, day one will be C69, D flat
69. Day two will be D69 and E flat 69.
Day three will be E69 and F69.
Day four will be G flat 69 and G69.
Day five will be A flat 69 and A69. And
day six will be B flat 6ix9ine and B69.
All right. In week number 34, we're
going to talk about rootless minor 6-9
chords. Once again, if you're on a minor
chord like a C minor, and you're
accompanying, you want to play a really
cool chord,
you can play chords like this.
Okay? Notice there's no root in this
chord. This is a C minor 69. And I'm
playing a very particular voicing. It's
a rootless voicing. Okay? So, how do you
play these chords? Well, you already
know what a C minor 69 is. It's that,
but we're going to put the six on the
bottom, and we have what's called a B
voicing. Okay, so it's should look very
familiar to you. If you put the third on
the bottom, you have an A voicing. Okay,
how do you practice these? Same thing.
We're going to go C minor 69. We're
going to go D flat minor 69. That's day
one. Day two will be D minor 69 and E
flat minor 69.
Day three will be E minor 69 and F minor
69. Day four will be F# minor 69 and G
minor 69. And day five will be A flat
minor 69 and A minor 69. You're doing
great. And finally, day six will be B
flat minor 69 and B minor 69. All right,
we're in week number 35. And in this
week, you're going to learn how to play
rootless dominant chords. And if you're
playing a blues and you're accompanying,
you want to play these cool crunchy
chords. This is the sound of bruteless
dominant 13 chords. And again, you
already know these chords. A C13
has all of these notes in it. Okay? We
usually put the D in as the ninth of the
chord and then the A is the 13. Well,
how do you play it? How do you make it
sound good? Well, it's very common for
jazz musicians to to put the third in
the bass and go 3 13 7 and 9. There's no
root. So, it's a rootless voicing chord.
And it is an A voicing because it has a
third on the bottom. You could also put
the seventh on the bottom, making it a B
voicing. Okay, so that's how you
practice it. Uh, day one, I recommend
that you practice C1 13 and D flat 13.
Then on day two will be D13 and E flat
13. By the way, you can drop the bass
here. Might sound a little better. Okay.
Uh, day three will be E13 and F13.
Day four will be G flat 13 and G13.
Day five is A flat 13 and A13.
And finally, day six is B flat 13 and
B13. All right, we're in week number 36.
And this is getting exciting because now
we're going to take those dominant
chords that you just played like this.
And we're going to alter them with
rootless voicings.
Okay? And this is how a jazz musician
would actually play these chords. They
don't just play these, you know, alter
dominant chords like this that I taught
you earlier because earlier I was
teaching you the notes. This is all
about voicing. How do you voice the
chord to play in a cool way? Well, if
I'm playing these crunchy chords and I'm
in the key of C and I'm on a a five
chord, the G, right? That's a rootless
voicing. What if I want it to sound
altered? Well, I might play it like
that. Okay? And that is very cool. I'm
voicing my G7 chord as an altered
rootless voicing chord. Okay. This
altered rootless voicing is called a
dominant flat 13 sharp nine. Okay? And
it has it has a very hip sound. That's
the sound. Okay? And you should know
this sound already because we talked
about it earlier. Okay? The way you play
this chord is you play a C7 and you put
a flat 13 and a sharp nine on it. It's
kind of like an A flat major over a C7
chord. You learned this earlier. Now
what we're going to do is we're going to
voice it. Okay? And what we're going to
do is we'll put the third on the bottom,
the flat 13, the seven, and the sharp
nine. You get a very crunchy C7
flat 13 sharp 9 chord. Okay, this is an
A voicing. This is a B voicing. If you
want to break it up and do uh what
previously was inversions, this would be
like an inversion on these chords. Okay,
how do you practice it? Let's go. Day
one, that's C7 with the alter notes and
D flat 7 with the alter notes. Okay. Day
two is D7 with the altered notes and E
flat 7 with altered notes. Okay. Day
three will be E7 and F. I know these
sound kind of weird, but this is how the
pros play them. Okay. Then day four will
be F# sharp 7 and G7.
Day five will be A flat and A. And
finally day six is B flat and B. Our
final altered rootless voicing is our
dominant flat 13 flat N. Very similar to
what you just learned.
That's what you just learned. The flat N
is that slightly different sound, very
common chord that jazz musicians will
use when they're accompanying and they
want to alter their chords. Okay, so
that's the sound of a dominant flat 13
flat 9 chord, right?
kind of a sad sound. Okay. How do you
play this chord? It's a C7 and we're
going to put the flat 13 and the flat N.
You see it's kind of like a C sharp
minor over a C7 chord. Okay. But we're
going to voice it in a nice way. We're
going to put the third on the bottom and
then we're going to come up flat 13 7
flat 9. Let's put the root down low. I
like that sound a little better. And we
start practicing. Day one, we're going
to go C7,
D flat 7. Okay, let's go. Day two,
right? This is going to be a D 7 to an E
flat 7. Again, we're adding all these
altered notes. Okay, day three will be
uh the E7
to the F7. Again, this has the flat 13
uh flat N on it. Then the G flat to the
G. That's day four.
Day five is the
uh A flat 7 to the A7. Okay. And then
lastly, day six is the B flat 7 to the
D7. Again, we're adding flat 13 flat 9
to all of these chords. Now, if you want
to go even deeper on rootless voicing
chords, you really want to understand
them and have some great exercises to
master them, check out our level six
foundations learning track at
pianowithjny.com. I have put together
fulllength courses on each of these
rootless voicings and we go deep on
them. So we explore major rootless
voicings, minor rootless voicings,
dominant rootless voicings, everything
we're talking about here, but we we go
slower and we go in much more depth. So
we talk about the chords. I show you
tricks to help you remember the chord.
We go through essential exercises. I
show you how to use these chords in
chord progressions and how to connect
different rootless voicing chords to
each other. and we apply them to tunes.
And that's really down here in our lead
sheet course. If you scroll all the way
down to the bottom, you take all of
these rootless voicings courses, major,
minor, dominant, diminished, and you
learn how to do them on lead sheets. So,
it is very comprehensive. If you really
want to learn rootless voicings, I
highly encourage that you go through
that learning track. So, I'll put a link
to that below. All right, welcome to
week 38. This is an exciting week
because we're going to dive into a new
voicing. And uh in our last few weeks we
talked about rootless voicings
which is a great way to accompany tunes.
But what if you wanted to play a
beautiful melody like what if you wanted
to play Autumn Le's
and you wanted to get this sound.
These are called block chords or locked
hands voicings. It's a really important
voicing to know if you want to play
beautiful chords like this, get this
kind of warm, crunchy sound. Okay. Now,
this technique is usually used to play
melodies. It's not really used for
accompaniment. So, if you have a melody,
let's say have a C melody and that
melody's moving. It's basically a way to
harmonize the melody
with three internal notes.
block chords. Really, really beautiful
chords. So, it's a melodic harmonization
technique and it gets it gets you kind
of a big band sound. Okay? So, it's a
voicing. It's we're taking chords you
already know and we're playing them in a
certain way to get a certain sound.
Okay? So, for block chords, the melody's
on the outside, you put three notes in
the middle all the time. It doesn't
matter what the melody is. That's the
melody. Put three notes in the middle.
If that's the melody, you put three
notes in the middle. Okay? That's kind
of the basic idea. So, we're going to
talk about major block chords. How do
you play major block chords? Very
simple. Take a six chord like this, a
C6. We're going to make C the melody and
we're going to put three chord tones in
the middle. That is a block chord on the
C melody. Okay? And you can do this for
each note of the scale,
but we're not going to go into that much
depth because that's going to be a lot
for you. We're just going to pick one
note of the scale and voice it as a
block chord. Okay? So, we're taking the
C and we're voicing it like this. That's
it. That's how simple it is. Then, we're
going to practice this in in all of the
keys. So, how do you play a block chord
on D flat 6? Bring it up a half step.
That's a D flat 6. That's your melody.
Okay, that's day one. Day two, D. That's
a D6 and an E flat 6. Okay, it's pretty
simple. Then day three will be E6 and an
F6. Day four will be F sharp 6 and G6.
Then day five will be A flat 6 and A6.
Day six is B flat 6 and B6. Okay. Once
again this is not for accompaniment.
This is a way to harmonize your
melodies.
Okay. Really beautiful. All right.
Welcome to week number 39. And this week
you're going to learn about minor block
chords. And if you're playing a tune,
it's a minor tune. You got a minor chord
and you want to get this
sound, you use minor block chords. And
it's the same as last week. Basically,
your melody stays on the outside. And
you're going to harmonize that with
three internal notes. Okay? Now, we're
not going to go over every single
melody. I just want to get you the main
voicing so you can start practicing uh
this particular voicing. So, how do you
voice this chord? Well, we have our C
melody. We're going to put three notes
in the middle. E flat, G, B flat. Okay,
this is a C minor 7. I'm playing all the
notes from the chord in the middle.
Melody note is on the other side. Okay,
very simple. How do you practice this?
Day one, C minor 7 to D flat minor 7.
Really simple. Okay. Day two is D minor
7 to E flat minor 7. Day three is E
minor 7 to F minor 7.
Day four is F sharp minor 7 to G minor
7. Day five is G# sharp minor 7 to A
minor 7. And day six is B flat minor 7
to B minor 7. All right. Welcome to week
number 40. And this week you're going to
learn how to play blocked chords on
dominant chords. And this is really
useful if you're on a chord like a G7
and you have a melody.
How do you harmonize it as a block
chord?
Right? That's how you would do it. It's
a really fun way to harmonize,
especially on a blues. is if you know if
you got a blues going
like that, you can do blocked chords.
Okay? Very, very hip. So, how do you
play these chords? Well, you've got the
melody C. You're going to put three
notes from the chord on the inside. In
this case, it's a C7. And that is the
block chord, right? Melody, internal
notes. Once again, I'm not going to
teach you all the notes from the scale
because that would be way too much for
this. I more want to teach you the
general voicing so you can get the sound
and the feeling of blocked chords in
your fingers. Okay? So C7's like this.
This is day one D flat. It's all on day
one. Okay. Then day two D7 and E flat 7.
Okay. Day three is E7 and F7.
Day four is F# 7 and G7.
Day five is A flat 7 and A7.
Day six is B flat 7 and B7. Welcome to
week number 41. This week you're going
to learn about blocked diminished
chords. And what if you had a melody on
embraceable U.
And you have a diminished chord like
that and you want to play a block chord.
How would you do that? Well, you'd play
it like this.
Okay? So, you can play these block
chords on diminished chords. How do you
do this? Well, let's say you have a a C
diminished like that. Well, you've got
the melody. We're going to use C as the
melody. You put the three notes from the
chord in the middle. That's it. That's
how you play a diminished block chord.
Now, you can use this on a scale,
but again, we're not going to get into
every note of every scale because it
would be way too much. But again, I want
you to get that feel of the diminish
block chord. Okay? So day one will be C
diminished and C# sharp diminished. Day
two will be D diminished and E flat
diminished. Day three will be E
diminished and F diminished.
Day four will be F# diminished and G
diminished. Day five will be G sharp
diminished and A diminished. And finally
day six will be B flat diminished and B
diminished. All right, welcome to week
number 42. This week you're going to
learn your final block chord. And for
this one, we're going to play our half
diminished block chord. And what if you
were playing a tune like Beautiful Love
and you have this half diminished chord.
How do you play this as a block chord?
Well, you play it like this.
Okay, it is a very hip sound. One of the
most beautiful chords,
you know,
in the book. Okay, so how do you play
this chord? Well, we've got C melody.
The chord is a half diminished chord.
So, there's a half diminished chord. And
then you put the chord tones in the
middle. That's it for your block chords.
Now, you can do this on the scale,
but we're not going to go into that much
detail because again, I just want to
teach you the basic voicing. Okay? So,
day one, C half diminish 7, C sharp half
diminish 7. Day two is D half diminish 7
and D sharp half diminish 7. Day three
is E half diminish 7 and F. Day four is
F sharp and G. You're doing a great job.
Day five is G sharp and A. Both half
diminish seven. And finally day six is A
sharp and B. Now, if you want to go deep
on your block chords and you want to
really understand them, I recommend that
you check out our level seven
foundations learning track over at
pianowithjny.com.
In this learning track, we go deep on
block chords and I teach you pretty much
everything you need to know about these
chords. And we're going to go deep on
each type. Major 7 block chords, minor 7
block chords, dominant seven block
chords. I'm going to teach you little
melodies for each one. So, when we do
major block chords, you're going to
basically focus on progressions that
just use major block chords. I'm going
to teach you how to connect these
chords. Uh, really important exercises
to master these chords. We're going to
work through multiple chord
progressions, work on connecting all the
various types of chords. And then
finally, we're going to apply it to lead
sheets. And this is the most important
thing. If you want to play real world
tunes with block chords, you need to
learn how to apply them. So, we apply
them to the top eight chord progressions
that you'll see in lead sheets. So, I'll
put a link to this learning track below.
All right, welcome to week number 43.
And this week, we're going to get into a
new voicing called the drop two voicing.
And this is a beautiful sound. I want to
show you what it sounds like on
Somewhere Over the Rainbow.
This is one of my all-time favorite
voicings, and it's very unique because
what I'm doing is I'm taking the block
chords that I just taught you, and I'm
dropping the second note from the top,
one, two, and I'm putting that on the
bottom like this. And this is what drop
two means. You're literally dropping the
second voice from the top to the bottom.
and it gives you a really beautiful
sound. Often times you get a 10th
interval
and it's just a lovely sound. Okay, so
how do you play your drop two voicing?
Well, this week we're going to focus on
our major drop twos. Okay, and it's very
simple. Here's what you do. You take
your melody. It's a C. There's the block
chord for it. And we're going to drop
the second voice from the top down to
the bottom. And that is the drop two
voicing on the C. Okay. Now you can
harmonize the whole scale
using drop twos, but again it's a little
too much for this video. If you want to
go deeply into that, you can learn that
over at pianowithjny.com. Okay, so
that's the voicing on the C. How do you
practice this? Well, day one it'll be C
and D flat. Great. This is a D flat
major 6 drop two. Day two will be D 6
and E flat 6. Okay. What about day
three? E6 and F6.
Day four F sharp 6 and G6.
Day five is A flat 6 and A6. And day six
is B flat 6 and B6. All right. Welcome
to week 44. This week you're going to
learn about drop two minor 7th chords.
And just like major 7 chords,
right, you can harmonize any minor
melody with drop twos. For example, if I
wanted to harmonize my funny Valentine
in drop twos, I could do that,
right? Any minor melody can be
harmonized this way. So, how do you play
this? Well, we take our C minor 7 block
chord that I taught you earlier and we
drop the second note here down bottom.
That becomes our drop two. Okay? Very,
very simple. Doesn't matter what the
chord is. If I'm playing this as a block
chord, I drop this note down to the to
the bottom. Okay, but we're going to do
this voicing to start. Okay, so this is
our C minor 7 drop two. And then you're
going to practice it on day one going up
to the C sharp minor 7 drop two. Okay,
day two will be D minor 7 drop two and
then E flat minor 7 drop two. Day three
is E minor 7 drop two and F minor 7 drop
two. Day four is F# minor 7 drop two and
G minor 7 drop two. Day five is G# sharp
minor 7 drop two and A minor 7 drop two.
And finally, day six is B flat minor 7
drop two to B minor 7 drop two. All
right, welcome to week number 45. This
week you're going to learn about
dominant 7 drop twos. And let's say
you're playing a blues and you want to
play your melody in drop twos. And let's
say your melody went
like that. You can harmonize it and drop
twos.
So, how do you play this? You take your
melody, three internal notes. It's a C7.
And we drop that second to the top note
down to the bottom. And that is a C7
drop two. It's that simple. Okay. Then
you can do it on D flat. There it is.
Okay. That's day one. Day two, D7 drop
two to E flat 7 drop two. Day three, E7
drop two to F drop two. It's that
simple. Okay. Day four, F sharp 7 to G7.
Beautiful. Day five, A flat 7 to A7. And
finally, day six, B flat 7 to B7. All
right. Welcome to week number 46. We're
going to continue our drop two chords.
And what if you have a diminished chord?
What if you're playing I'll Be Home for
Christmas.
You have this E flat diminished. And I
want to play this as a drop too. Can I
do that? Absolutely. So in this case, I
would go
like that. Okay. I just played
that diminished chord, right? As a drop,
too. Okay. So, how do you do this? Well,
let's say your melody is a C and the
chord is a C diminished. So, you put the
chord tones in the middle. You drop the
second note from the top down to the
bottom. And that's the drop two voicing
for a C melody on a C diminished seventh
chord. Okay, it's that simple. Okay, how
do you practice it? Day one like that.
So C diminished up to C# sharp
diminished. Day two is D diminished up
to D sharp diminished.
Day three is E diminished up to F
diminished.
Day four is F#ar diminished up to G
Day five is G# sharp diminished up to A
diminished.
And day six is A sharp diminished up to
B diminished. All right, welcome to week
number 47. This is the last week on drop
two chords. This week we're going to
cover our half diminished chords. And
what if you're playing a tune like
Beautiful Love
and you want to play your drop twos on
this chord? You can do that. Okay, it
would go like this.
Okay, really beautiful. Okay, so how do
you play these chords? Well, same as
before. Let's say the melody is a C. You
play your three chord tones in the
middle. That is a half diminished C
chord. And you drop the second voice
from the top down to the bottom.
Beautiful. Okay. Now, you can do this on
the full scale,
but that's a little beyond the scope of
this video. If you want to learn that,
you can in our full length course. Okay?
But for practice, get that first
voicing. And day one, start there and
then go to C sharp half diminish seven,
drop two voicing. Okay. Day two, we go
to D and then D sharp half diminish 7,
drop two voicing. Day three, it's E to
F. You with me? Then day four is F sharp
to G. Again, half diminished. Day five
is G sharp to A.
And day six is A sharp to B. Now once
again, if you want to go deeper on drop
two voicings and really understand them,
check out our level eight foundations
learning track over at pianowithjny.com.
Just like our other foundations learning
tracks, we go deep on this topic. We
explore each chord, major drop two,
minor drop two, dominant drop two, and I
show you how to play these voicings over
any melody note. So, if you have a
melody over these chords, you'll know
exactly how to play the voicing. I show
you essential exercises, how to play
these over different chord progressions.
We talk about the ideal fingering. Also
how to do little slideins to your notes
and then I show you how to apply drop
two voicings to a lead sheet. And this
once again is the best part of this
learning track because it's application.
You will understand how to do this on
your favorite tunes. So I'll put a link
to this learning track below. All right.
Welcome to week number 48. And this is
very exciting because in this week
you're going to learn the coolest, most
advanced voicing among them all. These
are called quartal voicings. Give it a
listen.
Okay, these sound super jazzy, super
cool, and all of the pros use this
voicing. So, what is a quartal voicing?
Well, a quartal voicing is a chord
voicing that is primarily built in
fourths or quarters. So, you want to
take your chord and you want to get as
many fourth intervals as possible. Okay?
But there's a very specific way to play
these chords. So, that's what I'm going
to show you. Now, these chords are
typically used for accompaniment. So if
someone is singing the melody or playing
the melody, you would typically play
these chords
as an accompaniment. However, you could
use them on the melody. For example, if
you were playing Let's Fall in Love,
you could use them on this tune. So in
this lesson, you're going to learn
quartal major voicings. Okay, this is
how to play a major chord like a C major
in quartals. Okay, so for this voicing,
we're going to start with the third, the
E. We're going to play the sixth, the
ninth, the fifth, and the root. And this
is a beautiful way of playing a major
chord if you want to accompany is to
play this voicing. Okay, it is a 6-9
chord, a C6-9 which you already learned,
but it is spread out primarily in fourth
intervals. You see all the fourths.
Okay, so that is the voicing you're
going to learn. So, how do you practice
this? Well, on day one, you're going to
go C and D flat. Day two is D and E
flat. Day three is E and F. Day four is
G flat and G. Day five is A flat and A.
And day six is B flat and B. All right,
welcome to week number 49. This week
you're going to learn minor quartal
chords. And what if you were playing a
minor chord progression and you wanted
to play as quartals? And let's say the
chord progression went like this. A flat
7,
G7,
C minor 7.
Okay. How would you play it in quartals?
Well, you could do it like this.
Okay. Very, very cool. Very, very hip.
Okay. So, how do you do this? Well,
let's say you have a C minor chord, like
a C minor 7. You can voice it like this
to get that quartal sound. We're
building this off the F, which is the
11. And we play F, B flat, E flat, G,
and C. This is the 11, 7, 3, 5, and 1.
And that's a very hip way of playing a
minor chord in quartals. Okay, so that's
how you do it. Now, you can harmonize
the whole scale,
but again, that's beyond the scope of
this lesson. If you want to learn that,
you can learn that over at
pianowithjny.com. Okay, so how do you
practice this? Starting on the C chord
and we're going to go up to the D flat
minor cordal. Okay, that's day one. Day
two is D minor quartal, D minor 11 to E
flat minor cordal.
Day three will be E minor 11 quartal to
F minor 11 cordal. Day four is G flat
minor 11 to G.
Day five is A flat minor 11 to A minor
11. And finally day six is B flat minor
to B. All right. What if you want to
accompany on a blues and the blues goes
and you want to use quartals? No
problem.
Okay, very cool. Very hip sound. So for
this, I'm taking my dominant chords like
a C7, and I'm building them like this.
Okay, primarily fourth intervals. I have
my third, my seventh, my ninth, my
fifth, and my root. I have a fourth, I
have a fourth, I have kind of like an
augmented fourth and a third there. But
that definitely gets you that quartal
sound. Okay, once again, you can
harmonize the whole scale,
but that's beyond the scope of this. You
can learn that over at Piano with
Johnny. Okay. So, how do you practice
this C7 or C9? This is day one. You go
to D flat.
Day two, we're going to go to D. It's a
D dominant chord. We're playing as a D9
up to E flat. That's day two. Day three
is E9.
This is an F9. Day four is G flat 9 to a
G9.
Day five, A flat 9 to A9
and B flat 9 to a B9. Sounds awesome.
All right, welcome to week number 51.
We're getting close to the end of the
year. And this week you're going to
learn how to play your diminished chords
as quartal chords. And what if you're
playing a Christmas tune like I'll Be
Home for Christmas
and you get to this diminished chord and
you want to play a quartal voicing.
Maybe you're accompanying. Well, you
might play it like this.
Isn't that beautiful? And then you might
go this on your two chord and this on
your five chord. Okay. So, how do you
play a quartal voicing on a diminished
chord? It's pretty simple. Okay. The way
I recommend that you do it, start from
your third. Play that double flat 7, the
A, the third. That's the flat three, the
flat 5, and the root. Okay. And what you
get here are a few augmented fourth
intervals. So that's an augmented
fourth. That's an augmented fourth.
That's an augmented fourth. Okay. And
that's beautiful. That is a C diminished
chord voiced in quartals or fourths.
Okay. Again, you can harmonize the whole
scale. We won't do that here. We're just
going to do the C. How do you practice
it? Day one, C diminished, C#arp
diminished. Day two, D diminished, D#
sharp diminished. Day three, E
diminished, and F diminished. Day four,
F#arp diminished and G diminished. Day
five, Gsharp diminished and A
diminished. And day six is Aar
diminished and B diminished. All right,
welcome to the final week.
Congratulations. You did it. You made it
all the way to the end of the year. And
for this lesson, you're going to learn
how to play quartal voicings on your
half diminished chord. Remember, this is
a chord you will see in tunes. And so,
it's really important to know how to
play cordal voicings on it. And so let's
say you're playing Beautiful Love. It's
a beautiful tune,
right? That first chord is an E half
diminished chord. How do you play a
quartal voicing on this chord? Well,
you'd play it like this.
Okay. Really beautiful. So, how do you
voice a half diminished chord as a
quartal voicing? Well, we're going to
use C as our example. And I like to
build it like this.
Okay, so we've got the 11th, the
seventh, the flat 3, the flat 5, and the
root. Okay, once again, we're trying to
go for maximum fourths. So, we have a
perfect fourth, a perfect fourth, and we
have an augmented fourth there. Okay,
really beautiful. All right, let's go
ahead and practice these. Day one will
be C half diminished. And this is D flat
half diminished. It's a quartal voicing.
Day two is going to be D half
diminished. and then D sharp or E flat
half diminished. Day three will be E
to F half diminished.
Uh this will be day four. This will be F
sharp to G. You're doing great.
Day five is G sharp to A. I know they
sound kind of weird, but this is the way
the pros do it. And then finally, day
six is A sharp to B. Now, once again,
just like the other voicings, if you
want to go deep on quartal voicings, you
can learn these in our level 9
foundations learning track over at
pianowithjny.com.
Once again, we go deep on each of our
different types of chords. Major
cortals, minor cortals, dominant
cordals, halfd diminished, diminished.
We go through how to harmonize the scale
in cortals. So, you can actually learn
how to harmonize any melody using cordal
voicings on any chord. We teach you
essential exercises, how to connect your
chords, and then how to apply them on
chord progressions and on tunes. And the
best course is our lead sheet course
because that's how you'll learn how to
apply these quartal voicings to actual
tunes. So, I'll put a link to that
below. Wow. Oh, wow. You did it. You
made it all the way to the end.
Congratulations. It is a big deal to
have worked through an entire year of
chords. There was a lot of material here
and this was truly designed to get you
through an entire year because if you
want to master your chords, you need to
understand the chords. You need to have
the right exercises. You need to be
inspired. So you hear the chords in the
context of tunes and chord progressions.
And so that was the goal here was to get
you excited, get you motivated, but more
importantly to get you on a path. And so
you made it. You've learned the 52 most
important chords. And by now, you should
have the confidence to go take your
favorite chord progressions and try
these chords on them. And when you
compare yourself now to where you were a
year ago, you should see a major
difference in your playing because you
worked through the material, you worked
through the exercises, and you got it in
your fingers. So, congratulations. Well
done. And if you want to improve other
aspects of your playing like scales and
ear training and accompaniment, you can
learn all of these skills over at
pianowithjny.com. We have dedicated
learning tracks that will help you. They
are made for your playing level. We have
beginner, intermediate, and advanced.
Also, you can study styles at Piano with
Johnny like jazz swing, Latin jazz, jazz
ballads, funk, rock, R&B, right? There's
tons of styles, so you can go deep. You
can really take your playing to the next
level. So, I encourage you to check out
all of our resources over at
pianowithjny.com. and I'll see you in
the next